Cumback mss.,1835-1904 LMC 1239
Lilly Library
Cumback mss.
1835-1904
Lilly Library
Cumback, Will, 1829-1905.
LMC 1239
2 Boxes
1 folio
The Cumback mss., 1835-1904, consists of the correspondence of Indiana congressman Will Cumback, 1829-1905.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
William Cumback, 1829-1905, was a lawyer and congressman from Indiana. He was born near Mount Carmel, Indiana, and completed his education at Miami University in Oxford, Ohio and at the Cincinnati Law School. He moved to Greensburg, Indiana in 1853 where he began to practice law. He was elected to the Thirty-fourth Congress (March 4, 1855-March 3, 1857) as a representative for the state of Indiana, but he was unsuccessful in his bid for reelection in 1856. He served as a paymaster in the Army during the Civil War and as Lieutenant Governor of Indiana in 1868.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged chronologically.
Scope and Content Note
The Cumback mss., 1835-1904, includes correspondence with prominent political figures, army officers, lawyers, poets, journalists, and personal friends.
The letters deal with national and state politics, 1854-1897; elections, 1856, 1860, 1880, 1884, 1896; army finances, 1864; slavery question as it related to Kansas, 1855; governorship of Montana, 1864; governorship of Idaho, 1870; minister resident to Portugal, 1870; position as a member of the cabinet of a Mexican mission, 1897; and efforts of friends to nominate John Addison Porter for governor of Connecticut, 1898. Included are also land grants, 1835-1856; commission as a lieutenant-colonel, 1865; certification of election to Congress, 1854; certificate of election to the Indiana Academy of Science, 1889; resolutions favoring prohibition and opposing the further extension of slavery by the Decatur County Democratic party; and a book of autographs of President Franklin Pierce, members of his cabinet, members of the Senate, and members of the House of Representatives of the 34th Congress, 1856. Among the correspondents are Timothy Patrick Andrews, Benjamin William Brice, Samuel Bryan, Will Carleton, Cassius Marcellus Clay, Howell Cobb, John Coburn, Schuyler Colfax, Neal Dow, Hamilton Fish, James Glover, Jr., Horace Greeley, Benjamin Harrison, Rutherford Birchard Hayes, William Steele Holman, Joe D. Howland, Samuel Porter Jones, Abraham Lincoln, John Uri Lloyd, William McKinley, John McLean, Louis Theodore Michener, J.D. Mooney, Oliver Perry Morton, Meredith Nicholson, Godlove Stein Orth, Alfred Pleasonton, John Addison Porter, John Sherman, William Tecumseh Sherman, Edwin McMasters Stanton, Alexander Hamilton Stephens, Thomas DeWitt Talmage, James Maurice Thompson, John Palmer Usher, and Lewis Wallace.
In addition, the collection contains printed speeches by William Cumback.
For digitized content, see Digital Collections.
Acquisition Information
Acquired: 1952
Legislators --United States.; Legislators --United States --Correspondence.; Indiana--Politics and government; Indiana--History.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- History; Cumback, Will. (William), 1829-1905; Cumback, Will. (William), 1829-1905 --Correspondence.; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865 --Correspondence.
- Kansas Election Contested. Includes speech by Will Cumback, 1856; (printed, bound) (Box 1)
- Book of Autographs. Congress, 1856; (bound) (Box 1)
- Biographical Material (Box 1)
- Western Christian Advocate. Clipping., 1850, Apr. 17 (Box 1)
- Glover, James, Jr. to Cumback, William, 1851, Feb. 4 (Box 1)
- Holman, William Steele to Cumback, William, 1854, Aug. 21 (Box 1)
- Colfax, Schuyler to Cumback, William, 1854, Oct. 27 (Box 1)
- Wright, Joseph A. Certificate of election of Cumback, William, 1854, Nov. 27 (Box 1)
- Colfax, Schuyler to Cumback, William, 1855, Apr. 16 (Box 1)
- Orth, Godlove Stein to Cumback, William, 1855, Apr. 14 (Box 1)
- Colfax, Scuyler to Cumback, William, 1855, Oct. 29 (Box 1)
- Bryan, Samuel to Cumback, William, 1855, Dec. 7 (Box 1)
- Cumback, William to Shombre [?], Henry J., 1855, Dec. 12 (Box 1)
- Bryan, Samuel to Cumback, William, 1856, Mar. 15 (Box 1)
- Howland, Joe D. to Cumback, William, 1856, Jun. 7 (Box 1)
- Mooney J. D. to Cumback, William, 1856, Jul. 14 (Box 1)
- Printed. Cumback, William. Speech..On the Politics of the Country... Washington, 1856 (Box 1)
- McLean, John to Cumback, William, 1857, Jun. [8?] (Box 1)
- Cobb, Howell to Cumback, William, 1857, Jul. 29 (Box 1)
- Printed. Cumback, William. Politics of the Country... Washington, 1857 (Box 1)
- Clay, Cassius Marcellus to Cumback, William, 1860, Jun. 15 (Box 1)
- Lincoln, Abraham to Cumback, William, 1860, Jun. 15 (Box 1)
- Greeley, Horace to Cumback, William, 1860, Oct. 24 (Box 1)
- Andrews, Timothy Patrick to Cumback, William, 1863, May 27 (Box 1)
- Usher, John Palmer to Cumback, William, 1864, Apr. 5 (Box 1)
- Andrews, Timothy P. to Cumback, William, 1864, Apr. 6 (Box 1)
- Cumback, William. Check to William Cumback, 1864, Nov. 3 (Box 1)
- Cumback, William to Brodhead, John M., 1865, Jan. 10 (Box 1)
- Brice, Benjamin W. to Cumback, William, 1865, Mar. 24 (Box 1)
- Cumback, William to Brice, Benjamin, 1865, Jun. 5 (Box 1)
- Stanton, Edwin McMasters to Cumback, William, 1865, Jul. 7 (Box 1)
- Adjutant General's office. Copy of discharge of William Cumback, 1865, Jul. 6 (Box 1)
- Morton, Oliver Perry to Cumback, William, 1870, Jan. 3 (Box 1)
- Fish, Hamilton to Cumback, William, 1870, Feb. 7 (Box 1)
- Newspaper facsimiles, 1704, Apr. 17 – 1881, Sept. 20. (Box 1)
- Morton, Oliver Perry to Cumback, William, 1871, Feb. 18 (Box 2)
- Colfax, Schuyler to Cumback, William, 1871, Feb. 20 (Box 2)
- Morton, Oliver Perry to Cumback, William, 1871, Feb. 21 (Box 2)
- Morton, Oliver Perry to Cumback, William, 1871, Feb. 24 (Box 2)
- Morton, Oliver Perry to Cumback, William, 1871, Feb. 25 (Box 2)
- Morton, Oliver Perry to Cumback, William, 1871, Feb. 25 (Box 2)
- Pleasanton, Alfred to Cumback, William, 1871, Apr. 1 (Box 2)
- Colfax, Schuyler to Cumback, William, 1871 (Box 2)
- Morton, Oliver Perry to Cumback, William, 1871 (Box 2)
- Printed. Cumback, William. Temperance and the Ballot-Box... Cincinnati, 1874 (Box 2)
- Sherman, John to Cumback, William, 1879, Nov. 11 (Box 2)
- Harrison, Benjamin to Cumback, William, 1881, Mar. 15 (Box 2)
- Stephens, Alexander H. to Cumback, William, 1882, Nov. 23 (Box 2)
- Hayes, Rutherford B. to Cumback, William, 1883, Jun. 14 (Box 2)
- Harrison, Benjamin to Cumback, William, 1884, Mar. 5 (Box 2)
- Michener, Louis Theodore to Cumback, William, 1884, Oct. 17 (Box 2)
- Sherman, William Tecumseh to Cumback, William, 1884, Nov. 11 (Box 2)
- Dow, Neal to Cumback, William, 1885, May 13 (Box 2)
- Jones, Sam P. to Cumback, William, 1886, Apr. 17 (Box 2)
- Harrison, Benjamin to Cumback, William, 1886, Apr. 30 (Box 2)
- Sherman, John to Cumback, William, 1887, Feb. 15 (Box 2)
- Hayes, Rutherford B. to Cumback, William, 1887, Mar. 14 (Box 2)
- Sherman, John to Cumback, William, 1887, Apr. 16 (Box 2)
- Indiana Academy of Science. Certificate of election of William Cumback, 1889, May 14 (Box 2)
- Sherman, John to Cumback, William, 1887, Jun. 8 (Box 2)
- Carleton, Will to Cumback, William, 1892, Jan. 12 (Box 2)
- Wallace, Lewis to Cumback, William, 1893, Dec. 13 (Box 2)
- McKinley, William to Cumback, William, 1896, Jan. 22 (Box 2)
- McKinley, William to Cumback, William, 1896, Jun. 29 (Box 2)
- Sherman, John to Cumback, William, 1897, Jan. 13 (Box 2)
- Sherman, John to Cumback, William, 1897, Feb. 26 (Box 2)
- Porter, John Addison to Cumback, William, 1897, Oct. 6 (Box 2)
- Porter, John Addison to Cumback, William, 1898, Feb. 5 (Box 2)
- Thompson, James Maurice to Cumback, William, 1898, Mar. 25 (Box 2)
- Wallace, Lewis to Cumback, William, 1903, Jan. 18 (Box 2)
- Coburn, John to Cumback, William, 1903, Jul. 27 (Box 2)
- Lloyd, John Url to Cumback, William, 1903, Oct. 26 (Box 2)
- Cumback, William. The Divine Right of Kings, 1904, Apr. 30 (Box 2)
- Nicholson, Meredith to Cumback, William, 1904, Aug. 23 (Box 2)
- Talmage, Thomas DeWitt to Cumback, William, Undated. (Box 2)
- Rebel Terms of Peace! Print of broadside (Box 2)
- Jackson, Andrew. Grant of land... to William Ryans (Foliobox 28)
- Pierce, Franklin. Grant of land... to Jane Coates (Foliobox 28)
- Democratic Party, Indiana. Decatur County. Washington Township. Resolutions (Foliobox 28)
- Pierce, Franklin. Grant of land... to Samuel Galloway (Foliobox 28)